so
i've got
a few questions that
i would like well i'll just the one main
question i have
is um
is specifically about something that
i've been experiencing
uh now coming to
quite a different place
mainly south africa and meeting
um
you know ordinary i would say people
who just live ordinary lives with lots of
just live ordinary lives with lots of
pressure um
you know how to the way they relax is
through maybe drinking and just having fun you
maybe drinking and just having fun you
know various types of fun
you know good good people and so on but
the main
the main thing i see is um
is that a lot of people's you know
people suffer from so much
loss and deep loss
and despite the the amount of friends
the amount of
fun the amount of alcohol
used to
find some peace and happiness
none of that helps with
the deepest of loss you know the loss of
a
husband the loss of money
the loss of money
the loss of your
mental faculties
and
yeah what exactly all
and the main the main one i mean the
most the most painful loss that i saw
the most painful loss that i saw
recently was someone had has recently
lost their
child their son their son
and
i mean these the parents are in such
tremendous turmoil such tremendous depression and
turmoil such tremendous depression and
pain
that you know it really shows you that
that suitor that says you know that one
who is dear and the you know that that's
the man who loses his son and the buddha
says yeah that's that's the way it is
with one when you lose one who is dear
you suffer from it
suffering so i'm wondering that what advice you
so i'm wondering that what advice you
know they asked me how to how to help
what can i do to overcome this suffering
well of loss
yeah see the problem with that is um
it's it's kind of too late to to be able
to just deal with that suffering
in other words most of their life life
has has already been lived unwholesomely
or unwisely
so now this loss the weight of this loss
now is the result
of everything else from before
because if if the life if the lives were
lived more wisely the weight of the loss
doesn't matter how great it is won't be
as heavy
so
you know when people usually ask at that
stage what do i do with this pain in
other words just uh
can you get rid of it for me
yeah so the first pretty much the only
thing they can do to to begin at least
facing the right direction of
development is to wealth you have to
stop resisting it
you have to accept the facts
you have to accept that you know your
child is gone that's just
and if you accept it then certain other
things might become apparent through
that such as
well yeah okay it came it went as that
sutta says you don't know where it came
from and you don't know where it's going
what is there to grieve for
um
but fundamentally you need to stop
resisting the pain of it internally
because the habit of the entire life is
to resist this discomfort
and indulge the comfort
so then when you're struck by a
you know unthinkable discomfort of
losing your child
you're resisting it
on on is a
very very very high levels
of resistance and that's why it hurts so
much not because you lost your child
it's just because
it is unacceptable to you that reality so
so
what what you can
do for them is just try to help them
accept it really not get rid of it just
accept it
but they might not want to do that they
might just want to get rid of the pain
and then not listen whatever else you
have to say but that's
that's as far as your help can go really
for somebody who's on that level
and that's the that's the thing actually
i did
in fact i i mentioned that that
you have to accept that
pain and be at peace with it
and you know obviously try to understand
it
those that feeling
but and they also mentioned to me that they
and they also mentioned to me that they
were
accepting it
you know every day
they face it
and that's true they do
but on at the same time they are facing it
on at the same time they are facing it
with
um
while being
intoxicated with alcohol
so
although you are intoxicated and facing
the pain you know you're talking about
the loss you're talking over and over
and about it crying about it
you are intoxicated
at the same time so are you really
facing it
that's what i mean like it's it's the
the weight of the loss the weight of the
pain is is not determined by what you lost is
is is not determined by what you lost is
determined by the state of your mind
and the state of your mind is has been
cultivated and it's determined in return
by your behavior
but whether you've been scratching the
edge whether you have been refraining
from it whether you've been developing
wisdom whether you haven't been
developing wisdom
so exactly the reason the reason why
they cannot not resist it so much
is because those are the mental habits
they've been cultivating their entire
life so a lack of restraint lack of composure
so a lack of restraint lack of composure
lack of patience all these things that
are normal normal normal for people but
then you realize because of those things
you are liable
to to the to the greater weight
of pain
than you would have experienced
otherwise if you actually developed you
know uh wisdom patience sense restraint
and virtue
but it again like you know people at
best of times don't want to hear about
virtue let alone when they're gripped by that
let alone when they're gripped by that
pain and resistance and you tell them
about sensory strain they're not going
to see a connection between the two at
all so
there's not really much you can do at
that stage unless you know they somehow
manage to calm down and then sort of
click in their mind that
hey how about is there anything that i
can do about this now you know like from
a more rational point of view as opposed
to just
just you know get rid of this pain while
i'm half drunk basically because i don't
know how to deal with it
then maybe you know they might be able
to listen and hear it
that you know the mind can be developed
you know the mind can be developed
regardless of what you've been through
but until then there's not really much
you can do
but what you can do though is
those who haven't
lost and those who might hear use that
as an example for them
like don't wait until it's too late
so you know essentially it's
learning to deal with pain
you know not
crave against it but also but to learn
how to deal with these little pains in
your life
well that's what the training is exactly
yeah so you you don't it's learning to deal
so you you don't it's learning to deal
with pain it's not like
learning a technique or a psychological
method it's really developing your mind so when
it's really developing your mind so when
the pain touches it the mind doesn't
move because it doesn't feel it
that's it so if the mind is not
developed the slightest pain will make
it move
so it's almost like a
um
like a like
like a
training you know like when you when you train a
you know like when you when you train a
response
like drilling in order for the right
response in a certain environment well
this is the same you're drilling
non-resistance to pain
and you do that on the level of these
small pains and discomforts that's the
training so that then when the pains of bigger
so that then when the pains of bigger
kind come the principle of
non-resistance is there to some extent
to some degree so that's the whole point
then then you will you will have that
space mentally because you're not
irrationally resisting that pain you
will have that space to see more
without needing without being
overwhelmed by the pressure to manage
that pain deal with it and get rid of it
but you will not have that space if you
haven't been training your mind in
regard to the pain
however subtle or however big you don't
need to wait for the big pains in order
to start the training quite the opposite
you know keeping the precepts already is
a form of pain for somebody who is not
trained in it
sense restraint moderation in eating
being watchful of your speech and
actions it's all a form of you know
confinement and discomfort because you
were spilling outside of it but see
that's a good pain that's a pain that
will make your mind develop and not move
so that then when pains of other kind
come pain of loss
where the loss of your life and health
and wealth and so on or loss of your
things that are dear to you
well there is some basis of training of
non-resistance towards discomfort but
you can't just wish non-resistance
you can either train it or not if you
trained it
mind will not resist it because it has
been conditioned to not resist
if you haven't it will resist even if
you wish for it to not resist
and that's the
you can really see the benefits of that
kind of training that you know training
in sealer well that's the wisdom yeah
see the problem with uh
there is no direct
seemingly the direct connection between sela
the direct connection between sela
and that
inability to suffer as much that
connection is not visible that's where
the wisdom comes in
the people that have discernment and
wisdom can can sort of see that
connection however faint it is
but people who who can't see it then it
will be even harder for them to commit
to the effort of seal and sense
restraint and gradual training
so that's why either you know you you
arrive at that effort through faith or
through discernment
but if people have neither
it's it's virtually impossible to train
rightly because why would you do it when
there is seemingly absolutely no good
reason for it
you have to understand do you
have to understand that
either understand it or just have faith
in it because you know
you have other you have faith in other
things that the buddha said so he also
said this so you just have faith in it
and on account of that faith you do the
work not just i have faith in it and i
don't do the work
the point is to do the work whether it's
done on account of faith or an account
of understanding and discernment doesn't
matter as long as you do the work
so how a person deals with the loss
don't wait until you lose something in
order to deal with the loss
that's already beginning of wisdom you
already recognize that
oh my children are all fine but
they could not be so
things could change
so is that thought scaring me am i
ignoring it or if say something like
that happens will my mind remain unmoved
or to what extent it would move
and you recognize oh that is a problem
that is a problem
so i could whatever they saw my children
or something or never have children yeah
but still
you are liable to your mind moving on
account of loss losing things that are
dear to you children or something else
doesn't matter
and that's what life is so you recognize
okay so it's about
training the mind to not move and not
lose perspective
and not be overwhelmed by pain that's it
not resist it
and how you train that
by that point see if if you already see
that as a worthy goal
to train
like to train towards being able to deal
with the loss before you lose things
then all the gradual training and things
the widow talks about will already make
much more sense
but you need to be willing to do it
right and willing to take time to step
step back and look at
what you are liable to well exactly yeah
that's like together to get a better
clearer perspective on the on the nature
of your situation
what you're liable to
uh where you're heading where your
actions and ambitions taking you are
they sort of
aligned with with with the nature of
things you're liable to or are they
based on ignoring the nature of things
you're liable to are you pretending
everything will always be fine forever
and act accordingly or are you actually
keeping that in mind that you know
your life will not last forever your
health will not last forever
things inevitably are subject to change
and it will have to happen
and there's a there's a kind of mantra that
there's a there's a kind of mantra that
i that i hear often
no
so it's like
sure i will get old
i will get sick maybe i will die you
know i might lose this and i might lose that
i might lose this and i might lose that
but i'll deal with that i'll deal with
that when it comes when it happens i don't
when it comes when it happens i don't
have to deal with that now
just just like that idea i'll deal with
it well ask yourself
just in in the limited experience that
you have in your life
was it better when you dealt with things
when you were prepared or where you were
unprepared which is which has a better chance of
which is which has a better chance of
dealing with it properly
when you were ready when you didn't lose
when you didn't sleep when you didn't
lose the sight of the problem or when
you were completely pretending oh i
won't worry about it and then when it
comes i'll deal with it
so is it better when you're trained to
deal with it
or is it better when you're untrained
and then just deal with it on the fly
you already know the answer
so better train for it
yes you'll deal with it when it comes
but it's better to be able to know how
to deal with it when it comes
not wait for it to comes and then hope
you're gonna kind of you know
manage to to float on top of it
and then when you when you look at uh
because you actually are always training
something you know exactly yeah yeah
you know exactly yeah yeah
you are always choosing and acting in
some direction
either it's going to be direction of
development that well the election that
contributes to is the development of the
mind and and removal of resistance
towards pain
or it's going to be a direction that
that basically
uh takes away from that development and
increases the resistance towards pain by
by habit by response
yeah yeah
so
and you know
you know
if i can just talk about like
uh
the habit of
say drinking you know alcohol
and you can see you know not not everybody's
you can see you know not not everybody's
an alcoholic and so on
but it's this you go to work
it's this you go to work
and there's and the pre you know every
day monday to friday or whatever and the
pressure builds up
the pressure of your duties and so on
and the only way you can relax
is to
you know through substances
through either distraction to alcohol
for example particularly alcohol as i'm
talking about
and that relaxes you you know that sort
of releases some of that pressure
so now what you are training yourself to
do is now i feel a bit of pressure
and i go to alcohol
and you can be relieved and feel relaxed
but what you are training now
is that every time you feel pressure
your way of relief is through alcohol
for example you know just to put it
so now
and are you liable to
have more pressure in your life through
other things such as loss
loss of your limbs loss of your
uh friends and family and so on
yes i am so
then when that pressure hits you what
are you going to do you're going to do
the thing that you've been doing all
this time to relieve yourself of
pressure yeah which is
all this time and then when you do that
so you have that you have a you have
your drink
and the pressure is not relieved
the pressure is not relieved
because it's so great
and so what do you have to do
you just you have to drink more but the
pressure is still not relieved so you
have to drink more and continue doing
that and that's that danger
and that's that danger
of having that one drink to relieve that
one small pressure yeah yeah the danger
is not in the alcohol the danger is in
the attitude
the danger is in the attitude of i will
use these external means to to pacify
myself which means you still use basically
which means you still use basically
forms of sensuality to find peace
which means you have a view that that is
peaceful and and that's the risk that's the peril
and and that's the risk that's the peril
so it's your attitude of giving into the
weakness for the sake of central peace
central peace
that's why having one drink even if it
doesn't make you drunk it's a problem
it's against the principle of training
well exactly exactly you you're giving
in to to that weakness however
ridiculous it is however however small
it is
the the whole principle of training is
to not seek
peace and escape externally but be able
to not move by be moved by it internally
so even if you just you know i drink
only on social occasions i don't get
drunk it doesn't matter you're giving in
to that pressure for the sake of comfort
for the sake of not standing out
whatever else it is
you are giving in
uh to the principle that is against the
training of your mind
so you are moving
you are moved by it
um so
when something bigger happens when some
greater pressure tries to move you again
you will leak through that opening
yeah yeah and then it's going to become
even bigger opening yeah
then it's just it's pretty much too late
in a way well that's that's what i said
in the beginning that's what it would
have meant like untrained asu or tujina
basically has no other does not know any
other escape from honor from arizona
painful feeling any other escape than
sensuality so whether it's alcohol
distractions whatever else it's all
based on the pleasures of your senses
so you need to be informed sutawa enough
to to recognize that that's a problem
although it feels the most natural thing
to do
it's actually a problem and i should
start refraining from going in that
direction although i don't quite see
directly why or how
i can make some sense that this is
aggravating my problem and perhaps sense
restraint is the way to go
and then you start the sense restraint
and then you get to learn more and then
you get to start seeing benefits for
yourself directly on account of that
training but not before you actually
start doing it because sometimes people
want to
have it all reasoned out and proven that
it will work before they even start
doing it
like you cannot understand how it feels
to be completely dry
while you never refuse well you well you
refuse to leave the water where you're
constantly immersed in water
so you need to actually physically
remove yourself from it and then you
won't need any intellectual convincing
and so on because oh you are drying up
properly
and that's that first step of faith
yeah either based on faith or some
degree of reasoning
but it needs to be done
it's sila comes first and he never
leaves it stays as a framework through
which you then grow and develop further
and again it's it's very important
to to realize the the nature of your
situation and start doing it before the pressure
and start doing it before the pressure
accumulates of the kind that you now
just cannot even cope with by the means
you're used to
i mean sometimes people can turn it
around you know but
but generally yeah you've been
scratching your ridge so hard there is
nothing else you know now in the world
except that
so you're pretty much like an animal
just that is responding to a stimuli
yeah yeah because again it's just it's
it's the accumulated
condition it didn't happen overnight
it didn't happen overnight
so that's why y'all now in order to
overcome it it's gonna take a while for
you to to undo everything that you
basically acquired
through the wrong actions and and lack
of wisdom
and i also thought you know how how
valuable it is to
um actually meet
someone who who has overcome
you know that very thing
well it's it's
it's like a divine divine messenger it
is
i mean you could see well how much
generally darkness there is in the world
in people's minds
by that i mean like they don't really
have a concept of what's right what's
good what's beneficial what it isn't
what brings mind to to develop what
brings mind to kind of decrease so
so
meeting somebody who can actually point
that out yeah yeah it's it's quite rare
and uh
because even you know you can
it's difficult to reason these things
but then when you actually see the
physical presence of someone who has
done it or whatever uh
that is that's more like oh yeah oh it's
oh it's possible it's possible yeah
that's the the summoner sonia the whole
the proper like the perception of
of somebody who's actually oh look
somebody did this
not just off seeing the being inspired
by the robe or the buddha statues i mean
oh no look possibility of freedom
has been actualized by somebody
actually yeah made actual so it's like
yeah made actual so it's like
maybe i can do it maybe i can at least
make some effort towards it
and that's rare
yeah yeah well it's rare to see people
who have actualized it and it's also
rare to to recognize the value of it
even if you see it yeah yeah
yeah yeah
but i think
i think most people
would recognize it you know it would
affect most people that sure see someone
completely on the other
scale yeah yeah they would yeah they
would not be able to
to completely not notice it
um
okay thank you for that sure